in my previous video we saw how a simple
Evolution algorithm could be used to
solve simple tasks such as balancing a
simple pendulum it's best to watch it
first if you want to know the details of
the algorithm used to perform the
training however this specific task was
very simple requiring only a few seconds
for the algorithm or even a human to
find a solution the various Solutions
found while very effective in solving
the problem were also very simple
with neural networks of just a few nodes
in this second part we'll see if a basic
algorithm such as the one described in
the first video can succeed in finding a
solution for a far more complex and
precise exercise balancing a double
pendulum first of all is it really that
much more complicated to have a double
pendulum instead of a single one
wouldn't it simply be twice as difficult
to illustrate the difference in
difficulty
let's start by comparing the performance
of a human in both cases first the
simple pendulum as we can see is pretty
easy to get the hang of it and only
takes a few minutes of practice
intuitively it's fairly easy to
understand what's going on if the
pendulum falls to the left you move the
C to the left to compensate and the same
goes for the
right now let's see what happens with
the double pendulum
[Music]
2,000 years
later we can see that there are several
problems firstly it's already very
difficult to stabilize the pendulum even
in the neutral downward position
secondly when by Chance the pendulum is
relative upright it's very difficult to
know what to do to hold it in place and
every failed attempt reinforces its
erratic movements following this
resounding failure let's take a closer
look at what makes the double pendulum
so complicated to
control first of all it's a highly
unstable system this means that when the
pendulum is in a state of equilibrium
the slightest disturbance is enough to
take it out of this state
this property makes the control window
much thinner than in the case of the
simple
pendulum secondly in addition to being
highly unstable the double pendulum is
chaotic a system is said to be chaotic
when very slight variations in initial
conditions lead to very different
results in this case three double
pendulums start with angles identical to
the millionth of a degree as we can see
this tiny difference leads to a wide
Vari variety of
trajectories it's a notion that's often
quite misunderstood and it's not at all
incompatible with determinism one direct
consequence is that it is difficult to
predict the evolution of such a system a
typical example of a chaotic system is
the Earth's atmosphere making weather
for casting quite
uncertain to carry out the physics
simulations for this project I used the
X pbd method which is very easy to
implement thanks to the excellent
research article made public by its
authors I will put a link to it in the
description as the trajectories of the
pendulums are quite hypnotic let's see
how the same thing looks with 4,000
double pendulums as in this example only
the trajectories will be drawn
[Music]
I think I could spend hours watching all
those beautiful moving geometries but
let's get back to our
subject now that we have a better idea
of how difficult the task is let's see
if the method used for the simple
pendulum can work here
too here are the Network inputs and
outputs will be using as with the simple
pendulum all the network will control is
the speed of the Cod I'm not showing the
hidden neurons and connections here
because they'll be created during the
training phase so I don't know in
advance what the network will look like
the scoring function used is very simple
each agent gains one point per second
when the free end of the pendulum is
above a threshold this threshold is
equal to the length of the pendulum -
5% let's start the training using 1,000
agents each of whom will have 100
seconds to collect as many points as
possible given the score function the
maximum possible score is 100
[Music]
points one eternity
later unfortunately even after letting
the algorithm run long enough to break
my interface the score is nowhere near
the theoretical Max of 100 points I'm
not going to show here the best solution
because it only looks like a crazy
blender and I wouldn't want to trigger
an epileptic seizure a potential problem
with this first approach is that the
score function doesn't differentiate
between a solution that does a lot of
rotations and one that does fewer but
stays above the threshold for longer to
try and correct this problem I then
tried another score
function this time at each point in the
simulation the score is incremented by
the time currently spent above the
threshold to the power of 8 it's a bit
of an exaggeration but I wanted to see
what effect it would have so I went a
bit wide the delta T is simply used to
normalize the score to the simulation
frequency in addition time is reset to
zero as soon as the pendulum Falls below
the threshold all this should give a big
advantage to solutions that keep the
pendulum above the threshold for longer
than
others let's see how this new evaluation
function works with a new training
session it's important to note that the
theoretical maximum score now has
nothing to do with the old
100 the score looks pretty high but I
have no idea what it represents as a
solution
so let's have a
look it's a little better but it's still
not enough there's no balance and the
Pendulum goes back into blender mode
very quickly maybe I'm just unlucky
let's try again this time the training
lasted much longer so let's see the
results even if the state of the neural
network leaves me a little skeptical
once again it's really disappointing
even if it's still better than my first
attempt I've tried lots of different
configurations and score functions
without success at this point I was
really considering giving up especially
after coming across an article that
concluded that they hadn't managed to
get a satisfactory res solution using a
serious reinforcement learning
method after a long pause on the subject
an idea came to me perhaps the task is
simply too complicated for my
rudimentary algorithm why not try
starting with a simpler version and
gradually increasing the difficulty my
idea being that it should be fairly easy
to transition from one solution to
another gradually since similar problems
should have similar solutions for this
new training
I'm going to start by using a very low
force of gravity and a very high air
friction coefficient then each time the
best current solution reaches a Target
score gravity will increase by 1% and
friction will decrease slightly the
evaluation function will be the same as
at the very beginning as it allows me to
set a threshold that I can easily link
to a degree of success I've also reduced
the time of each iteration to 60 seconds
to speed up
training since the theoretical maximum
score is 60 I set the Threshold at 50
this means that over the minute of an
iteration agents will have to spend at
least 50 seconds above the
threshold let's see what it all adds up
to in this diagram the scores are shown
for each iteration each time a score
exceeds the threshold it is marked in
green and the difficulty increases
[Music]
the score Evolution shown here is not in
real time so I've added time indications
to give an idea of how long this kind of
training really takes after over 100
iterations gravity has quadrupled so
let's see what the current solution
looks
[Music]
like it's a rather abrupt solution but
it's pretty clean let's keep
[Music]
training let's look at the solution
found after 14
[Music]
minutes I'm very happy to see that
there's now the beginnings of
compensation to counteract the loss of
balance induced by a much stronger
gravity
[Music]
a few iterations later gravity has
reached its Target
[Music]
value the network has come a long way
since last time it has found a
whiplash-like movement and is
stabilizing much closer to the center
however I feel that the simplest thing
has been done for the moment since the
high friction greatly reduces the
instability and chaotic aspect of the
double pendulum this is quite obvious if
you look at what happens when you
deactivate the neural network control
it's like the simulation takes place
underwater let's resume the training and
see what happens when friction
approaches zero
[Music]
it's still not bad but you can see that
the network has grown considerably in
the meantime
after almost 50 minutes the friction is
fairly close to
[Music]
zero however the solution is starting to
degrade with strong rapid
oscillations this kind of strategy is
neither natural nor pretty it doesn't
bode well for the rest of the training
[Music]
after a few more minutes the friction
reached
[Music]
zero honestly I was expecting a more
jerky solution after all the previous
failures it's very satisfying to have
proof that it can be done it's always
easier to persevere when you know
there's something to find in the
[Music]
end and this time we can clearly see the
characteristics of a double pendulum
when the neural network is
disabled I'm very happy to have
succeeded in getting a solution but I'm
not completely satisfied I still find it
a bit unrealistic and
abrupt let's tweak the evaluation
function a little and see if that
improves
things to avoid strong velocity
variations I've divided the score by the
sum of the variations between successive
values returned by the network this
should encourage smoother Solutions
let's start from scratch with this new
function and see if it produces better
results
[Music]
let's see what we have after 8
minutes to its credit this solution is
not abrupt now I'm wondering how much it
will be able to adapt to more
complicated
conditions after 20 minutes progress
slowed considerably and the score fell
for this second session the threshold is
very different because the evaluation
function has changed it is also more
difficult to find a threshold
intuitively although far from perfect
this solution is much more natural and
smooth I really like the movement I
still wonder whether it will be possible
to maintain this Elegance in the future
[Music]
after a very long stagnation of over
1500 iterations the target gravity value
is finally
[Music]
reached despite a slightly more unstable
execution the movement is still clean
and smooth
[Music]
now it's time to reduce friction to
zero I'm going to fast forward to the
end because it will take another 20,000
iterations to get there for a total of 8
hours of training or 46 years of
simulated
[Music]
time this new solution is much better
than its predecessor with far fewer
jerks and a movement that feels quite
natural however I think there's still
room for
improvement the last thing I'd like to
tray is to also divide the score by the
total distance covered by the cart to
favor the most stable
Solutions let's start training again
with these new
parameters a quick check after 8 minutes
to get an idea of the direction taken by
the
algorithm it would appear that the
solution is both very smooth and stable
which is rather encouraging for the
future I'm going to move on very quickly
with this iteration as everything went
pretty well right up to the end training
was also fairly quick lasting around 2
hours in total
[Music]
so let's see what the solution looks
like for this new
[Music]
training in my opinion this is a very
good solution fast smooth and very
stable I'm really happy with the end
result
still there's something I'd like to
check as with the simple pendulum I
wonder if the double pendulum can
withstand random disturbances let's
check it out right
[Music]
away I am really pleasantly surprised by
the robustness of the system even if of
of course the disturbances are less
severe than with the simple
[Music]
pendulum this solution is really good
and I'm very happy with it but to tell
the truth there's still a little
something that bothers me all this time
the neural network was controlling the
speed of the cart which means that the
acceleration was somehow infinite which
isn't very natural this forced me to
modify the evaluation function to obtain
correct results
I wonder to what extent controlling the
cart acceleration instead might not be a
simpler and more physically correct
solution for this latest experiment
we'll have to make a few modifications
in several places first of all we'll
need to adapt the neural network a
little by adding a new input that will
allow it to know the card's current
velocity then to make things easier I
decided to increase the execution
frequency of the neural network on until
now this frequency was 60 HZ but now it
will be 480 HZ finally because of the
previous modification the Precision of
simple floats will be a problem I've
therefore decided to use double floats
everywhere as these are immensely more
precise let's take a quick example to
illustrate the problem this tiny code
simply performs Oiler integration on a
float X for a simulation running at 480
HZ
when you run this code here's what you
get you can see that unfortunately X
hasn't moved as the following test
confirms now that everything's ready
let's see if we can get something that
[Music]
works it seems that a solution has been
found for the time being let's see what
it looks like
it's a little less precise and rapid
than previous versions but it
[Music]
works a few minutes later gravity
reached its maximum value quite fast
[Music]
actually again it's a little less
elegant than before but the solution is
smooth and stable
you can see that the friction doesn't
vary at a constant rate which is because
I manually adapt the difficulty
according to the performance of the
[Music]
solutions I forgot to mention that the
score function used is the very first
one simply proportional to the time
spent above the threshold
[Music]
and finally after a somewhat complicated
Final Phase we reach a friction of zero
let's see how the network
[Music]
performs I'm really pleasantly surprised
by the stability of the solution I'm
happy a solution was found at all
[Music]
all in all I'm glad I was able to find
different solutions using such a
rudimentary
algorithm however there are quite a few
limitations the training remains long
lasting around 2 hours there were quite
a few small adjustments to be made
manually and none of the solutions
managed to regain equilibrium after
collapsing also in around two out of
three cases training is unsuccessful and
and stagnates however I think this kind
of method is still an interesting way of
getting started in the future I'd like
to explore other more sophisticated
algorithms to Benchmark
against thanks for watching I'll leave
you with a few other Solutions I was
able to find
[Music]