machine learning is a Hot Topic and for
good reason it has unlocked the ability
for our computers to perform a whole
host of tasks that we simply didn't know
how to program manually this fascinating
discipline is also a lot of fun to try
out on your own but can be quite
daunting due to its many mathematical
and programming prerequisites especially
if you want to write everything from
scratch yourself a branch of machine
learning called reinforcement learning
is particularly appealing it promises to
teach a program to perform complex tasks
by letting it carry out its own
experiments in a given environment
however this set of techniques requires
an excellent understanding of the
machine learning principles on which it
is based in this video I'm going to
present a very simple method which you
can do yourself from scratch and which
requires much less theoretical knowledge
naturally this method is also far less
powerful than the current
state-ofthe-art but
does at least allow you to build up an
intuition about the fundamental
principles while playing around with
some amusing results to give a concrete
example of how to use this method I'm
going to apply it to a classic case
stabilizing an inverted pendulum on a
cart this technique is heavily inspired
by the famous neat algorithm
neuroevolution of augmenting topologies
but in a simplified
version the principle of this algorithm
is to evolve neural networks
both in terms of their architecture and
their weights the advantage of building
the neural network as the training
progresses is to start with very few
parameters to optimize at a time this
aspect being a notorious limitation of
evolutionary
algorithms the type of networks used is
a little different from traditional
models based on interconnected layers
since unlike the latter their
architecture is designed to evolve as
training
progresses here we use dags directed a
cyclic graphs to represent neural
networks dags are a kind of graphs in
which there are no Cycles networks are
made up of three types of nodes inputs
whose value comes from a measurement of
the environment hidden nodes whose value
is not accessed directly but is used for
the internal workings of the network and
outputs whose value will be used to
interact with the
environment the first thing to do in
order to execute comp network of this
type is to determine the order in which
to perform the
operations to do this we can use
topological sorting to order nodes
according to their ancestors so that a
descendant is always placed after its
parents to sort nodes we start by
creating a list containing all nodes
without incoming
connections then as long as this list is
not empty we extract the nodes from it
one by one and for each one we delete
its outgoing connections then add it to
the list of sorted nodes if one of The
Descendants has no more incoming
connections we add it to the list of
nodes to be
[Music]
processed at the end of this process we
obtain the list of sorted nodes
[Music]
next we set the value of the inputs with
the data coming from the environment and
following the previously defined order
we apply the operations one after the
other until we reach the
outputs for each neuron there are three
operations to perform add the bias to
the current sum apply the activation
function to this result and for each
outgoing connection multiply this value
by the connection weight and add the
result to the sum of the destination
neuron in this example the activation
function is the identity function for
the inputs and hyperbolic tangent for
the other
neurons The Peculiar nature of this type
of network makes it slow to run unlike
layered networks which exploit Matrix
multiplications that are massively
parallelizable now that we've seen how
the neural networks used in this
approach apprach work let's see how they
can be trained to perform the required
task training is carried out in
successive iterations each of these
iterations takes place in three stages
evaluation selection and
mutation the aim of each iteration is to
generate a population n+ one containing
agents that perform better than the
generation
n the first step is to assess the
current population on the task in hand
to do this we use a fitness function
that Associates a score with each agent
representing its ability to perform the
task finding a good Fitness function can
be tricky but it can have drastic
consequences on the final result as
we'll see
later the second step is to select the
agents who will participate in the next
iteration to do this they are first
sorted by score then the top 30% are
directly added to the next population
unchanged to generate the remaining 70%
we draw individuals from the population
as many times as
necessary each agent has a chance of
being selected which is proportional to
its
score the final step is to evolve the
networks so that they produce slightly
different and ideally better results
each selected Network then has a chance
to undergo a mutation which can be a new
connction connection a new neuron
created by splitting an existing
Connection in two or a modification of
an existing weight it is also possible
for the network to remain unchanged
we've seen how the algorithm works as a
whole now let's apply it to a concrete
case balancing an inverted
[Music]
pendulum for this problem the
environment is very simple consisting of
a fixed length rail on which a cart can
move with a pendulum connect Ed to
it here are the network inputs and
outputs we'll be using as you can see
all the network controls is the speed of
the cart on the horizontal
axis the activation function used is reu
for the hidden neurons and hyperbolic
tangent for the
output for this first test we'll use a
very simple Fitness function giving the
network one Point per second when it
manages to keep the end of the pendulum
above a threshold this threshold is
equal to the length of the pendulum
minus a small
margin to train the network I'll use
1,000 agents who will have 100 seconds
at each iteration to achieve the best
possible score in this case 100 points
to speed up the process the execution of
the iterations is multi-threaded
allowing the agents to experiment in
parallel
I was actually surprised to find that it
was quite fun to try and balance it
myself albeit rather complicated I must
admit I practiced a little so I wouldn't
look too
ridiculous let's take a look at training
with this Fitness
[Music]
function we can already take a look at
where our network stand after a few
seconds of training at the 10th
iteration
and here are all the active agents
trying their best to maximize their
score let's get back to training and
follow the agent's progress which so far
has been quite
rapid with a score of over 99 let's see
how the network performs
it's not too bad but there's a strong
oscillation maybe a better solution will
emerge after a few more
[Music]
iterations unfortunately it's even worse
as I said earlier the fitness function
plays a fundamental role in the quality
of the final result let's try to modify
it a little to force networks to find
more stable Solutions
for this second trial the fitness
function will be quite similar to the
First with the score still increasing if
the pendulum is kept above the threshold
but this time the score will be divided
by the angular velocity of the pendulum
we can already see that progress is a
little slower even if it's still very
much there let's move forward a few
iterations now that we've reached 99
points let's take a look at the
[Music]
result it's already much better the
strong oscillations have disappeared and
the stable state is reached very quickly
however I'd be happier if the pendulum
stabilized in the center of the rail
let's adapt the fitness function again
to push the solutions towards the
middle in addition to the previous
modification the score will be reduced
in proportion to the distance to the
center
progress is very rapid at first before
slowing down and gently increasing let's
fast forward and see where it takes
us it's exactly what I wanted to see the
balance is reached very quickly and then
the cart remains almost
stationary this solution was found quite
quickly in less than a minute in real
time
of course in simulated time it's a
different story since 1,000 agents spent
150 times 100 seconds trying out random
things all in all almost 6 months of
training were required which isn't
incredible particularly when compared to
the few minutes it takes a human to
learn to perform the same task although
execution remains less optimal and
precise out of curiosity let's look at
another possible result by changing the
training seed
another rather elegant solution although
the final network is a little more
complex than last
time after playing with all these
solutions for a while I wondered how
sensitive they were to external
disturbances to test this I added random
pulses that are applied to the end of
the pendulum in an irregular pattern
let's load the same neural network and
see what what happens with the addition
of random
[Music]
pertubations I was very pleasantly
surprised to find that the system
remained stable even with the
disturbances I was expecting more
sensitivity from the solution
[Music]
I then wanted to interact directly with
the pendulum myself to better test its
robustness overall I'm very pleased with
these results although the method used
is very
rudimentary however the simple pendulum
seems to be a bit too easy of a problem
even for this algorithm that's why in
the next video we'll see how this same
algorithm copes with a double pendulum
making the problem far more complex due
to its extremely unstable and chaotic
nature
[Music]