in my last two videos on AI training I
presented a rudimentary but highly
effective technique for solving simple
tasks in this case balancing a single
and then a double Pendulum In the first
very simple case a robust solution was
found in less than a minute the
resulting neural network was also very
compact comprising no more than three
hidden neurons in the second case it was
more difficult with training lasting
between 2 and 8 hours was and only
succeeding in finding a solution one
time out of four on average the training
required a slightly different strategy
as the algorithm was initially unable to
find a solution it was therefore
necessary to gradually increase the
difficulty of the task via gravity and
air friction to achieve a
result the networks were also much
larger with around 30 neurons and
several hundred
connections the solutions found however
were rather elegant and could withstand
small perturbations without losing
balance but in the event of loss of
equilibrium none of the solutions
managed to restabilize in this video I'm
going to compare my previous results
with a modern reinforcement learning
algorithm po I'm really curious to see
what the differences will be
particularly in terms of training time
solution quality robustness and network
size to make the comparison we'll now
need to interface a physics simulation
with po as this algorithm is much more
complex I decided to use existing tools
this time and it turns out that ISAC Sim
is perfectly suited to this
[Music]
project Isaac Sim which is part of the
Nvidia Omniverse ecosystem offers a
whole range of tools for robotics
related
simulations in particular it enables
machine learning algorithms to be run in
Virtual physics environments simulations
and algorithms can then be executed
entirely on the GPU resulting in
excellent performance Nvidia helped me
in the making of this video by providing
me with Hardware allowing me to better
exploit the capabilities of these tools
ISAC Sim doesn't provide reinforcement
learning algorithms directly so to use
po we'll need ISAC lab a py Library
providing a whole set of algorithms
capable of interacting with ISAC Sim
what's impressive about ISAC lab is that
the physics simulations are accurate
enough to be able to exploit the results
of virtual training in the real world
even for tasks requiring precision and
Agility like this
one Isaac lab is highly flexible
allowing the import or creation of
custom robots as we'll see later
to make things clearer here's an
overview of the stack we'll be using at
the base is omnivos of which Isaac Sim
offering a simulation solution for
robotics is a part next comes Isaac lab
an OP Source python Library available on
GitHub that lets you interact with Isaac
Sim simulations
programmatically Isaac lab also includes
reinforcement learning libraries
preconfigured to work with Isaac s
simulations data each of these libraries
implements its own version of the PO
algorithm for uses requiring specific
tools or learning methods Isaac lab's
modular architecture also makes it easy
to integrate external custom
libraries Omniverse and ISAC Sim are
very easy to install Isaac lab is a
little more technical but the detailed
documentation explains everything step
by step in just a few minutes all the
tools are correctly installed and now
let's see what the included examples
look like in particular the simple
pendulum several things are worth noting
firstly po takes full advantage of the
scalability offered by Isaac Sim the
greater the number of Agents the faster
the training here 4,096 agents are
exploring in parallel then as is often
the case with examples involving
pendulums the swing up is not included
each episode begins with the pole
pointing upwards at a slight random
angle finally we can see that training
for this task is extremely fast this
first example shows that the
installation works and will enable us to
familiarize ourselves with Isaac Sim
what remains to be determined is how to
create a double pendulum how to specify
a reward function how to describe the
inputs and outputs and how to configure
the algorithm
accordingly all this may seem a little
daunting at first but at least we can
start from a working example to start
things off gently let's modify the
pendulum task to include the swing up it
turned out to be much simpler than
expected in fact each task is described
using python in a dedicated file this
file contains many of the answers to our
questions as it specifies the actions
observations rewards and initial
conditions of the task the whole thing
is fairly intuitive and it shouldn't be
too complicated to adapt this to our
needs in this case the event CFG class
is used to define the initial state of
each pendulum at the moment we can see
that a random angle and velocity are
effectively applied at the start we'll
then modify these values to place the
cart in the middle of the rail and set
the angle to P radian so that the pole
is pointing downwards pretty simple
let's run the training to see if it
works the python configuration also
specifies the conditions for resetting
the task here there are two when the
elapse time exceeds a given value or
when the cart ends up outside a
specified range on the rail I'm going to
skip the first minute of the training
because there isn't much exciting going
on
once again training is very fast and I
find it super cool to watch the
algorithm improving his technique in
real time so far I'm pretty impressed
even if it's still a simple task
compared to the double pendulum I'd be
curious to test the robustness of the
solution by interacting with it to
interact with the solution I loaded the
final network with a single agent in
Isaac Sim I can then apply forces to the
system with the mouse and see how it
adapts to these perturbations
overall I found the result
satisfactory especially after only 2
minutes of training no matter what force
is applied it always comes back to
equilibrium in the
end now that we've mastered this simple
task let's tackle the more difficult
problem of the double pendulum the first
thing to do is to create the robot that
will perform the
task once again the documentation is
excellent providing a comprehensive
tutorial explaining all the steps
involved in creating your own
robot now that we've got that down let's
Dive Right In and create our double
pendulum
[Music]
in just a few minutes I managed to
create a first working version on the
other hand it's particularly ugly but
it's a start and it's just the beginning
of what we can do with Isaac Sim and
Omniverse there's a fundamental feature
I have haven't yet exploited that could
really make our pendulum
Shine the entire Omniverse ecosystem is
based on USD which stands for Universal
scene description USD was originally
created by Pixar who then made it open
source since then its use within the
industry has grown steadily thanks to
the many advantages it offers in
addition to
interoperability as its name suggests
it's a 3D scene definition standard that
offers total compatibility between all
software that support it this is really
helpful when you're using lots of
different tools each with their own
format which is a very common situation
in many 3D workflows USD is a great
subject in itself because it's so
versatile and offers lots of different
functionalities especially when it comes
to collaboration in a nutshell USD is to
to 3D what USB is to connectivity or
HTML to the web for this project we're
going to use it to import a double
pendulum model made with blender
directly into Isaac Sim export is very
simple from blender which supports USD
natively I'm a little skeptical however
because beyond the geometry the model
contains many complex materials and I
wonder how well the export will retain
all these features
once in Isaac sim a simple drag and drop
opens the USD file it would seem that
everything is fine after all as the
import has retained all the
characteristics of my
model this whole process was
impressively smooth now that the model
has been correctly imported we need to
turn it into a real physical double
pendulum this turns out to be very
straightforward all I have to do is
recreate all the joints between the
various parts of the system
[Music]
it doesn't take long to obtain a
functional and much more pleasing double
pendulum ready to be used for
training all that remains is to create a
new task based on the simple pendulum
one surprisingly there aren't that many
modifications to do the action is the
same the Network's output is still a
force applied to the cart we will also
use the same observations as for the
simple pendulum that is the position and
velocity of each joint the biggest
changes are in the reward function which
must now take the second pendulum into
account and I used the opportunity to
favor Solutions centered on the rail
I've increased the inference frequency
from 60 HZ to 120 to cope with the much
higher accuracy requirement of the
double pendulum balancing task and I set
the maximum duration of an iteration to
10 seconds a second python file is used
to configure Poo's
hyperparameters we can see that for the
single pendulum the network comprises
two layers of 30 two neurons somewhat
arbitrarily I chose to use four layers
of 128 neurons for the double pendulum I
don't have much experience in
reinforcement learning so we'll see if
that's
[Music]
enough as with the simple pendulum there
are still 4,000 and 96 agents exploring
in parallel here apparently the added
complexity of of the double pendulum has
no effect on Isaac Sim's
[Music]
performance after just 40 seconds the
agents were already able to balance the
system I'm genuinely impressed I didn't
expect such efficiency especially as I
didn't use the incremental difficulty at
all as in my version in less than a
minute po found a viable solution to the
problem including the swing up
[Music]
let's see the result after 5 minutes of
training frankly it's a clean and very
stable solution I'm repeating myself but
I simply find the speed of convergence
of this algorithm
fascinating especially as I'm far from
being an expert in the field I wonder
what training would be like with the
right
settings one aspect remains to be
assessed the robustness of the system in
the event of disturbances my own
solution could cope with small ones but
if these tip the pendulum the network
was unable to recover let's take a look
at P's solution to see how it Stacks
[Music]
up like my solution it can handle minor
jolts with ease but what about stronger
ones no problem here for Poo's approach
which recovers without a hitch whatever
happens to the pendulum the system
always returns to
equilibrium once again I'm very
impressed especially as all this is the
result of only a few minutes
training it's now time for a quick
summary comparing the two
approaches the difference between
training times is probably the most
spectacular
to get a solution with my evolutionary
algorithm it takes between 2 and 8 hours
and in many cases the training is
unsuccessful with po a solution is found
after just a few minutes and is
satisfactory in the vast majority of
cases what's more it does not require
training with increasing difficulty the
Gap is even more striking when we
compare the duration of training in
simulated time this measure is used to
estimate the efficiency of an algorithm
in extracting information from
observations on average the evolutionary
algorithm needs 34 years of simulation
to find a solution PO on the other hand
needs just 8 and 1/2 days this
difference perfectly illustrates the
power of gradient descent the two
algorithms simply are not in the same
league as for the quality of the
solutions I find both clean and
efficient I might give the edge to The
evolutionary solution for its perfect
centering although I'm well aware that
with more expertise it would certainly
have been possible to obtain a more
refined solution with
po finally the difference in network
size is
enormous The evolutionary solution
comprises 30 new neurons when po employs
a network with four layers of 128
neurons each for a total of
52 when it comes to connections the
difference is even more striking
compactness is one of the advantages of
this evolutionary approach which is
simply not efficient enough to optimize
a very large number of parameters as for
PPO it's certainly possible to obtain
much more compact Alternatives if you
know how
this comparison between a homemade
implementation of an old algorithm and
the state-of-the-art in reinforcement
learning shows just how far artificial
intelligence has come in recent times
however I don't think that evolutionary
algorithms should be overlooked they
enable us to solve simple problems very
quickly and are an excellent entry point
into the field of machine learning this
video was also an opportunity for me to
discover I Club a brilliant tool for
easily manipulating these Cutting Edge
algorithms and playing with realtime
physics
simulations many thanks again to Nvidia
for providing me with high-end hardware
and for the technical support I received
via the omnivos Forum download omnivos
Isaac Sim and Isaac lab to try them out
they're completely free I will put the
links in the description thanks for
watching